ladies and gentlemen. do you know people who post pictures of themselves almost every day snap like my new watch snap west lake in spring and snap here's me middle of a speech competition from streets to campuses. people are obsessed with taking photos of themselves.
but when photography was first introduced to china in nineteenth century, it traumatized a generation.
with a draw tube shaped like a cannon, the dazzling firework at exposure like that.
and most horrifying of all the bizarre feeling of her own face staring back at you on a piece of paper and.
witchcraft, they say an evil ritual taken away our spirits.
as the development of technology moves, the will of history forward.
it was always accompanied by fear.
judging in retrospect from the era of selfie craze, of course. we would want to tell those benighted people of the past if you're not yourself. won't be sucked into a camera and this is exactly what i want to tell people of the present fear, not because when technology revolutionize our lives, humanity frames.
look at our world now.
the debate between scientists and humanists never seem to set our minds at rest when scientists are bragging about generalizing five g sixty. the humans say you're providing easy ways to infringe on personal privacy.
when scientists.
brag the ai as humans ultimate assistant.
the civil writer say we're where they might develop consciousness of their own.
once i a self proclaimed, the physicist talked to my powers from the school of humanities about teleportation is that theoretically we can transport anything from here to there instantly by disintegrating the stuff here and reconstructing an identical one there, but i was instantly bombarded with so soon you are going to transport people in this way, would you.
but we won't be the same person after teleport. will my consciousness be instantly terminated upon disintegration here, leaving only a duplicate of me to be reconstructed there so innocent bystanders upon hearing these fantastic debates panic oh no, the geese are going to read our meals. the robots are going to take off the earth.
teleportation is going to destroy thousands of people every day, leaving a word full of clothes.
but none of this.
is actually going to happen.
because humanists are not alarmists and scientists are not geeks.
humanists point out part and ethical issues with the hope of correcting them, and scientists listen to their suggestions rationally to make adjustments as well as amendments.
just like the first pioneer who modified the camera to make it less scary, we can always improve technology with humanitarian care.
we can enhance the security of networks by introducing quantum cryptography.
we can put restrictions on a.i. to prevent rogue elements as for teleportation or maybe it's too risky to transport humans, but we can still relieve a considerable burden of beijing traffic by taking care of the delivery system.
so taking a glimpse into the future. what exactly do i see.
not the ai rain dystopia where humans are reduced to slaves. not the post apocalypse desert after a nuclear war.
but a future where humanity thrive with technology as its instrument of success and technologies right with humanity as its code of conduct. just like how we market nineteenth century people for being fearful in front of a camera, our future generations were also we wondering why we had feared some of their daily routines in the first place as they reach ever high dimensions and rome across the stars. thank you.
think your contestant.